welcome to the listening Time Podcast
hey everybody this is Connor and you're
listening to
[Music]
episode21 of the listening Time Podcast
thank you all for listening I hope
you're all doing great the topic of
today's episode is a really interesting
one and I think that most of you are
going to like this one because it's
something that most of us or maybe all
of us are currently dealing with or are
at least uh having to think about a
little bit which is
inflation right we are
experiencing a lot of inflation in many
countries around the world and a lot of
places have had uh a lot of issues
because of inflation economies have been
hurt and people have had uh a hard time
because of
inflation in this uh recent period and
remember that I'm recording this in
2023 so if you're listening to this in a
future year then this might not be uh as
relevant but during this time uh that
I'm recording ing this episode uh
inflation is a Hot Topic and many people
are talking about this and complaining
about it and so I thought this would be
a good topic to discuss in today's
episode so we'll talk about um what
inflation is uh the causes and effects
of inflation we'll talk about some
countries that have very high inflation
right now and what people do during
times of high inflation so this should
be a really interesting episode uh I'm
excited for it and before we start
remember that I have my new podcast
available now which is called us
conversations this is an exclusive
podcast you can sign up for it if you
feel ready to to uh listen to
conversations at real speed in English
so in this new podcast I talk to
different English teachers from around
the United States in different parts of
the country and we have a normal
conversation about many different topics
and I provide the transcript for you uh
with the definitions of of key words and
phrases that we use during the
conversation so I know that a lot of you
have been waiting for this type of
content from me and now it's available
so if you'd like that you can click on
the link in the episode description
below this episode that's
patreon.com USC
conversations and of course you can sign
up for my membership
if you want my specialized training to
help you understand native speakers when
they speak fast the link is also in the
description below this episode and if
you like this podcast please share it
with anyone else you know who's learning
English and please give it a fstar
rating and write a review all right
let's get started are your ears ready
you know what what time it is it's
listening
time okay let's talk about inflation
first of all what is inflation people
might have different definitions of
inflation and people think about this
topic in different ways but I'll just
give an overall definition that most
people would be happy with and that is
inflation
means that there is an increase in
prices and a fall in purchasing power uh
what does purchasing power mean this
just means that your money buys less
stuff you can't buy as much stuff with
the same amount of money that you used
to be able to buy so that's a fall in
purchasing power so that's inflation and
many of us are struggling right now with
inflation in our different countries
because uh over the past couple years
we've seen a lot of inflation around the
world so let's talk about some causes of
inflation um there are different causes
it's not just one particular thing um
there could be uh certain things that
come from the demand side meaning the
consumer uh who is buying products or
services and there could be causes from
the supply side uh from the people that
are producing these goods and services
maybe the cost of production has gone up
for them and they can't produce as much
stuff or they need to raise prices
because of problems with the supply side
so there are a lot of different things
that can uh affect and influence the
inflation rate um but let me just uh
talk about maybe the overall idea of
what causes inflation of course this
isn't necessarily the most detailed
explanation but I think it kind of
summarizes everything so inflation is
caused by uh having more currency
units that are
chasing goods and services without a
greater increase in production of those
goods and services okay that might be uh
a little hard for you to understand let
me explain it so a currency unit just
refers to $1 or one Euro or whatever
right um a currency refers to the
different uh money that we use in
different countries right so the dollar
is a currency the euro is a currency Etc
so when we have more
dollar for example in
circulation but we don't have the same
increase in the production of goods and
services if there isn't an increase or
if there's a decrease or if there's an
increase but not enough of an increase
this will result in higher prices it
will result in inflation
think of a basic example right in the
Years 2020 and
2021 in many places for example in the
United States the government gave out a
lot of free dollars to people a lot of
people received stimulus checks and uh
there were other forms of stimulus that
produced more dollars more of these
currency units right however this didn't
increase the amount of goods and
services that were created and so we had
more dollars but we didn't necessarily
have more goods and services so people
might have felt richer because suddenly
the they had more money in their bank
account however when you just increase
the money supply that simply means that
prices will go up because now there is
more money in the system uh that is
chasing the same amount of goods and
services so that makes the price of
these things go up that's just logic
right so uh that's what happens uh when
you suddenly increase the currency and
there are more dollars or more Euros um
it makes prices go up right and you can
increase the amount of currency in a
system without price
inflation if the production of goods and
services increases even more than the
increase in uh the currency so a good
example of this was in the late 1800s in
the US when there was actually an
increase in the overall currency uh the
amount of currency units in the system
however prices actually went down how
did that happen well it's because there
was so much
production of goods and services and
that production was even greater than
the increase in the money supply so even
though the money supply expanded prices
actually went down because more things
were produced so you can see that there
are a lot of factors at play um in terms
of uh the causes of inflation and how
infl
happens let's talk about the effects of
inflation now so when there's
inflation when there's a lot of
inflation especially people are not
encouraged to save uh people are
actually encouraged to spend and invest
for example let's pretend you have
$10 and the rate of inflation is very
high right now and you put your $10 in a
bank account uh a savings account and it
has a low interest rate and that
$10 uh increases a little bit but the
rate of inflation is 10% maybe and then
maybe next year your $10 has grown to
$105 in that savings account but the
purchasing power has gone down for those
$10 now instead of needing $10 to buy a
hamburger it takes
$11 so even though you saved $10 and you
earned a little bit of Interest the rate
of inflation went up higher and you
actually lost purchasing power you see
how that works so people are not as
encouraged to save because usually the
rate of inflation kills their savings it
makes their savings uh less uh valuable
so instead of that people are encouraged
to spend money now because uh prices
increase in the future if there is
inflation and so people want to buy
things now before prices increase and
people want to invest their money in
something that will provide them a
return that's greater than the rate of
inflation so if inflation is
10% you want to earn at least
11% uh with your Investments so that you
can beat uh the rate of inflation and
your purchasing power won't go down
right so
in the opposite scenario if there is
deflation this has the opposite effect
it encourages people to save money
because their money will actually be
worth more next year than it's worth now
so you put your $10 in a savings account
and maybe that grows to
$105 um next year or maybe it doesn't
maybe it's just is $10 still however
that $10 buys more next year uh because
prices have gone down and you've uh
received an increase in your purchasing
power so that's what happens when
there's
deflation and in many cases deflation
might result in less investment because
people don't need to chase the best
forms of investment uh to beat the rate
of inflation because there is no
inflation there is deflation so people
don't need to search for those
Investments they can just uh keep their
money in a bank account and it grows in
real value over time because prices are
going down so you see how inflation and
deflation encourage the opposite
Behavior right and when it comes to
wages uh the word wages just refers to
the amount of money that you make uh
specifically the amount of money you
make per hour um so when it comes to
wages and your
income this never keeps up with
inflation if there is high inflation
so if there's 10% inflation your wages
are probably not going to go up by the
same amount uh at the same time right so
you might receive raises over time your
boss might raise your
salary however your overall purchasing
power is not increasing because prices
are increasing faster than your wages so
even though you might make more money in
one year your real wage is actually less
when I say your real wage I'm referring
to your real wage adjusted for inflation
right so even though your income might
increase life continues to get harder
and harder to afford the verb afford is
used to say that you can pay for
something so if I say I can't afford
that car I'm saying I don't have enough
money to buy that car so life gets
harder and harder to afford because your
income doesn't increase as fast as
inflation
increases and another reason why life
gets harder to afford is because
interest rates often rise uh when we
have high inflation and so for example
it might be uh a lot more expensive to
get a loan uh from the bank or to pay
back uh money that you've borrowed so
things get harder to afford overall and
so of course there are many negative
effects of inflation this is something
that hurts people very badly uh in many
cases so what are some countries that
have high inflation right now in
2023 so I'll mention a few of them here
but there are many other countries that
also have pretty high inflation
currently but here are a few of them
Venezuela uh has around
400% inflation that's really really high
so imagine prices today being
400% what they were last year right
that's not a good situation of course uh
in the country of
Lebanon um recently there was over
250% inflation really really high um in
Argentina uh inflation has been a big
problem in recent years and the rate of
inflation has reached to over
100% um and inflation is also a big
issue in Turkey right now um it's close
to 50% at the time of recording this so
there are some countries right now that
are dealing with major problems because
of really high
inflation and maybe you live in one of
these countries and you know exactly
what I'm talking about it's not a good
situation to be in and how about the US
well of course the US doesn't have
inflation anywhere near some of these
other countries however in June of
2022 um it reached
9.1% which was the highest rate in many
years in the US uh and to be honest that
99.1% is
understated uh when I say that it's
understated I'm saying that in reality
it's more so when we see uh the official
rate of inflation in the US we know that
in reality it's even higher higher than
what they're saying it is but that
99.1% was the highest in many years the
rate of inflation has gone down uh this
year however at the time of recording
this uh we still have inflation so
prices are still
increasing uh but by less right because
uh we don't have deflation yet prices
aren't going down yet
but they're going up at a slower Pace
than they were a year ago for example uh
but the US has dealt with a lot of
inflation recently and the percentage in
the US might not seem very high to you
depending on where you live but people
definitely feel it here and lastly what
do people do during periods of high
inflation or hyper inflation well one
thing is that people uh who live in a
country with really high inflation they
tend to immediately exchange their
money um once they've earned it for
another more stable currency or for
precious metals when I use the phrase
precious metals I'm talking about things
like gold and silver
right so for example uh in Turkey right
now if people receive their income in
the local currency they might try to
immediately exchange that for US dollars
or for Euros or for gold for example so
that they don't
lose uh purchasing power so that their
money does doesn't um
deteriorate uh by tomorrow or next week
they want something more stable right so
that's something that happens in many
places um but in a place like the US it
doesn't happen the same way because we
have the US dollar and so the US dollar
is generally considered to be the safe
stable currency that other people look
to uh for Refuge when I say the word
refuge I'm talking about uh protection
and safety right so we have this
currency already so when we deal with
inflation we can't do the same thing
with another currency the way that other
countries
do this because the people in those
countries might exchange their currency
for dollars but we already earn dollars
and so most people in the US don't
really have this option uh we don't
think about uh exchanging our currency
for another more stable one right we can
exchange our dollars for precious metals
of course and some people do that but we
don't really have the option of um
exchanging our dollars for a more stable
currency because we have the currency
that people usually view as the safe
currency right the safest and most
stable one right so that's a little bit
different in the US and a lot of times
during periods of really high inflation
the government in uh that country will
make it illegal to um exchange over a
certain amount of money uh for dollars
or Euros or whatever and if that's the
case then people create a black market
for dollars or Euros or whatever so
people exchange this
illegally uh because they need a more
stable currency
and if the government doesn't let them
have one then they'll get it illegally
so that's another thing that happens
something else that happens is that
people try to invest their money uh
quickly in something that's going to
give them a real return uh they don't
want to just hold their currency they
might exchange it for another currency
or precious metals or invest it in
something um that will gain in value um
to a greater degree than uh the rate of
inflation and uh so they might try to
buy something some asset uh so that they
can beat inflation by the way the word
asset in this context refers to
something that you
own uh that can uh produce a positive uh
economic effect for you for example like
owning a property right or owning a
stock so people might try to find assets
that will grow uh faster in value uh
than the rate of inflation right and
another thing people might do is buy
things now rather than later because
they know that prices will increase in
the future so they buy things now and in
really extreme examples of
hyperinflation people will just
immediately buy things once they get
paid in their local currency they might
immediately buy milk or buy rice or buy
something because they know that it's uh
better to do that right now uh than wait
a week when the price is higher right
and uh if they buy something real now it
will increase in value uh very very fast
right and one last thing that might
happen is that people might leave their
country unfortunately and look for a
more stable situation so that's what
might happen in times of very high
inflation all right I think that's all
for today uh hopefully this time topic
was interesting for you uh hopefully it
was
educational and I know it's not the
funnest topic but I think it's
interesting because a lot of us are
dealing with this now remember that you
can sign up for my new podcast if you
want to hear real
conversations uh in English uh with the
transcript of course uh the link is in
the episode description below this
episode and you can also join my normal
membership if you want my specialized
training and if you want my Advanced
podcast episodes you can become a
listening Time family member and if you
like this podcast please share it with
anyone else you know who's learning
English and please give it a five-star
rating and write a review all right
thank you for listening to this episode
and I'll talk to you on the next episode
of listening
time
[Music]